The iShell is an alternative to using shell commands. For a ZOS user familiar with iSPF,
this can be easier to use. If you've completed any of the lab exercises so far, you'll also
be familiar with the iShell. Most of the functions that can be performed using the
iShell are related to the file system. A regular user can use the iShell to work with
directories, regular files, FIFO special files and symbolic links. A sysadmin can do all
of this and a good deal more, including mount and unmount a file system, set up ZOS Unix
users and groups, change attributes for ZOS Unix users, create character special files and
set up the root file system. Now if you look across the top here, you'll see a number
of pulldown menus and we're showing the directory menu here. The first option, directory
list, has been enhanced to include all sorts of features such as sorting columns, using
color highlighting and executing actions based upon cursor location. Here is the directory
list and it, you ready for this? Lists the files of a directory. Other new features of
the directory list since ZOS version 1.6 include wildcard support on the directory list and an
option to inherit the command line position from the previous dialogue. Sorting is available
for any column that can be displayed even if that column is not selected for display.
A secondary sort column can also be specified. This support allows you to arrange the list
by file type for example and within file type by another attribute such as name, date or size.
The highlighting enhancements allow entries in the directory list to be highlighted based on
a number of different criteria. There are no defaults defined so if you want to highlight
entries in the directory list, you must set it up to do so. The terminal must support colors for
this feature to work. The use of this feature on terminals that don't support color might
produce some interesting and wildly arbitrary highlighting for file names. We can set the
highlighting criteria for things like when the sticky bit is on, when a file is marked as
executable and so forth. Support has been added to ISPF for the processing of ZOS Unix files.
This support includes the ability to edit, browse, create, delete, rename, copy and replace
ZOS Unix files. This new support is implemented as a directory list utility known as the ZOS
Unix directory list utility available as option 17 on the ISPF utilities menu. This initial
implementation of the directory list utility provides a subset of the functions that are
supported by iShell. The set of functions supported by the directory list facility are
aimed to assist with basic tasks undertaken by programmers. The utility is not really aimed at
users like the ZOS Unix file system admins. Now as much as possible, the directory list
utility is designed to behave and support commands similar to the data set list utility
which is ISPF option 3.4 and that's done on purpose to assist users who are familiar with
the operation of the data set list utility but maybe have less experience working with ZOS Unix
files through utilities such as OMVS or iShell. When option 17 on the ISPF utility selection panel
so that's ISPF option 3.17 is entered the ZOS Unix directory list utility entry panel is displayed.
This panel supports the following options blank to display a list of files in a directory and
p to print a list of files in a directory to the ISPF list data set. For either option the user
must enter in the path name field the path name of the directory they want to display or to
print. If a path name is not entered well then the user's home path is assumed. The ZOS Unix directory
list panel is displayed when the option field is left blank and enter is pressed on the entry panel.
This panel lists all the files in a directory. The information for each entry in the directory
is displayed in column fields across the screen. Now keep in mind that the number of columns
displayed depends upon the available screen width. This example here shows the initial directory
list display on a terminal with a screen width of 85 and a screen depth of 31.
Horizontal scrolling is supported using the right and left primary commands or function keys 11 and
10. This example shows the directory list display after entering the command right 5 on
the directory list shown on a previous screenshot. The order in which columns appear in the directory
list display and the size of the fields can be customized using the ZOS Unix directory list
column arrangement panel. This panel is accessed by using the pull down menu displayed under
options on the action bar on the ZOS Unix directory list entry and display panels.
Here the user can change the order in which the columns are displayed and the width of
the column fields. If a column fields width is set to zero the column is not displayed
in the directory list. In the next video we'll discuss how to perform tasks by using the
directory list utility panels.